Finding Aid for Southwestern Michigan Urban League records, 1962-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Southwestern Michigan Urban League records 1962-2007
Southwestern Michigan Urban League.
85808 Bd 2
Interracial, non-profit, non-partisan community service organization in Battle Creek, Michigan (formerly Battle Creek Area Urban League) founded in 1966 and affiliated with the National Urban League. Series include: History, Administration, Correspondence, Reports, Meetings, Programs, Community Memberships, Public Relations, Events, Battle Creek Area Urban League Guild, and Visual, Audio, and Digital Materials.
23 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was first deposited by Battle Creek Area Urban League in 1974 (donor no. 5499 ). Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Southwestern Michigan Urban League (formerly Battle Creek Area Urban League) is an interracial, non-profit, non-partisan community service organization affiliated with the National Urban League. The seventh affiliate to organize in Michigan, its initial mission followed traditions of Urban Leagues in similar city centers -- to secure equal opportunities for minorities and the disadvantaged through community planning and non-confrontational negotiations with employers and government officials. The League continues to implement its mission through advocacy and bridge building, along with research and services in areas of education, employment, health, community and economic development. Governed by a board of directors, programs are administered by an executive director and staff. Corporations, foundations, and the United Way of Greater Battle Creek provide programmatic funding.
In 1953 Roy Norris, a field representative of the National Urban League visited Battle Creek and met with the Human Relations Committee, which later expanded and became the Battle Creek Area Council on Human Relations. Nine years later, under the leadership of Evelyn Golden, the Council's employment committee invited Paul I. Phillips, executive director of the Grand Rapids League to attend one of their meetings to discuss a youth incentive program. His visit rekindled interest in the League and in July of 1962, the Council wrote to Whitney M. Young, Jr., Executive Director of the National Urban League, requesting affiliation information.
Early in November 1963, Evelyn Golden was named chair of the Urban League Study Committee of the Council of Human Relations. In February 1964 an associate director of the national organization visited Battle Creek to confer with community leaders. A second twenty-one member Urban League Study Committee was appointed by the Calhoun County Community Council in July 1964. Its major goal was to conduct a study documenting the economic and cultural conditions of African Americans in Battle Creek.
Dr. Warren Banner, research director of the National Urban League, was invited to assist with the survey. His report, "A Review of Economic and Cultural Problems in Battle Creek," indicated that a wide gap existed between black and white residents of the community in areas of health, education, employment and housing. Following review of the 145 page document, the Committee recommended to the Community Council and the United Fund that a League be established by January 1966 with a budget of $18,000. Agencies and organizations including the City Commission, Council of Churches, General Foods Corporation, Michigan Bell, W.K. Kellogg Company, AFL-CIO and YWCA offered support.
In June 1965, Whitney Young, Jr. visited the city to meet with a group of twenty-five Battle Creek business and industrial leaders. The following November the League was accepted as a member agency of the United Way with funding scheduled to begin January 1967. A $6,000 grant from the Kellogg Foundation made it possible to begin operations earlier and in September of 1966 Milton R. Robinson was named executive director and Lillian Chase secretary. A board of directors was appointed consisting of twenty-nine Battle Creek citizens selected to represent a cross section of the community. Evelyn Golden was elected board president; Ray Briggs vice president; Lucille Mitchell secretary; and Thaddeus Taylor treasurer. The Board held its first meeting on March 28, 1966. On May 17 the League was formally accepted by the National Urban League as an affiliate.
Battle Creek Urban League quickly established itself as one of the major social service agencies in the area. Active committees focused on employment, health and welfare, education and youth incentives. Meetings were held with the school board and school officials, job training programs were developed, voter registration drives were instituted, and the League became a strong advocate for fair housing. Whitney Young, Jr. was guest speaker at the first annual dinner held in March 1967. Director Milton Robinson wrote a weekly column, "Robinson on Race," for the Battle Creek Enquirer and News.
The early 70s were marked by the development of broad new programs. "New Thrust" was designed to address problems in youth employment and housing through block clubs and leadership training. A project developed in collaboration with four other cities focused on moving minorities into building trade unions. A grant from the Michigan Department of Education funded a food program for low-income children. From the late 1970s through the early 1980s, however, the League suffered from a series of short-term executive directors, lack of support staff, depressed membership, weak record keeping and financial management, reducing the effectiveness and efficiency of programming efforts. The lowest point in this period was in October 1976 when the League's food stamp operation came under charge of mismanagement.
In 1982 Benjamin Richmond was appointed executive director. Richmond immediately became active in local civic organizations, increased community support, relocated the offices of the League, and hired additional staff. During his tenure, the Battle Creek Area Urban League realized the restoration of fiscal solvency and an increase in membership, committee participation and programming. The Employment Procurement Program assisted adults in finding jobs. The Linear Park project involved youth in the construction of a Battle Creek landscaped parkway. The Community Interest Group, a collaboration with local businesses and organizations including the W.K. Kellogg Company and the Battle Creek Area Chamber of Commerce, provided employment services to area young people. Challenge IV, a joint venture with Kellogg Community College, offered both education and employment services to students planning on pursuing higher education. Additional programs linked teenagers with senior citizens, assisted single parents, developed neighborhood watch groups, provided scholarships, and hosted an annual community Family Day.
When Benjamin Richmond resigned in 1988 to head the Urban League in Louisville, Kentucky, Joyce Brown was selected to head the organization in Battle Creek. During Brown's tenure the agency continued its active involvement in civic affairs, solidified its administrative structure, and developed long-range strategic plans. In that same year the National Urban League called attention to a pressing nationwide need for educational initiatives, including increased community involvement and partnership with neighborhood schools. Brown established an Education Department and launched the Education Initiative Program with three components -- parental involvement, mentoring and tutoring. The Education Department also managed a stay-in-school program and a program to assist high school drop-outs. Meanwhile, the Employment Department continued the work of Challenge IV, the Community Interest Group, Linear Park, and job assistance for adults. Outreach also became a major focus. Family Day continued as an annual event, bringing neighborhoods, churches and civic groups together each summer; Urban League Sunday was celebrated each February; and a community networking reception designed to promote community awareness and problem solving was inaugurated.
In 1992 the Battle Creek Area Urban League, under the leadership of James Graham, changed its name to Southwestern Michigan Urban League. During this decade, the organization continued to focus on employment, education and youth issues. Programs like STRIVE, and the Urban League's contract compliance monitoring services served to increase minority employment opportunities and ensure equitable work environments. Likewise, youth programs such as the Community Leaders Program, and various scholarships offered and organized by the Urban League provided the youth of Battle Creek with guidance and educational opportunities.
After the departure of James Graham in 1997, the Southwestern Michigan Urban League went through interim CEOs Joyce Brown and Dizzy Warren before hiring Kenneth Little to the position in 2002. Little's tenure saw the Urban League, under the guidance of Chairman of the Board, John Harper, focus its attention on the goal of realizing the dreams of disadvantaged children in Battle Creek. To this end, programs such as "I Saw the Light," and "Can You Hear Me," were enacted, as well as collaborative efforts with the Urban League Brass Band. After Little's departure in 2004, Carl Word was hired to the position of CEO and President.
The records of the Southwestern Michigan Urban League span the years 1962-2007. The League's mission of providing and administering services for minorities and the disadvantaged, as well as internal operations, are reflected in the records, which consist mainly of administrative and program materials, correspondence, minutes, reports and proposals. While the years represented incorporate tenures of numerous executive directors, the records most fully document leadership provided by Benjamin Richmond (1982-1987) and Joyce Brown (1988-1992).
The Southwestern Michigan Urban League Records are relevant to the study of the administration of African American social service organizations, especially Urban Leagues, within the context of particular communities. The collection is strong in illuminating the effectiveness of collaboration -- civic, business and educational groups addressing interrelated community issues. Both Richmond and Brown maintained high profiles on numerous boards and committees working in Battle Creek to solve social problems and promote economic development.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Battle Creek Area Urban League (Mich.); Battle Creek (Mich.). Housing Commission.; Civil rights--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Education--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Housing--Michigan--Battle Creek.; National Urban League.; Community organization--Michigan.; Southwestern Michigan Urban League.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Social conditions.; Battle Creek Area Urban League.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Children.; African Americans--Education.; African Americans--Michigan--Battle Creek.; African Americans--Organizations.; African Americans--Political activity.; African Americans--Women.; African Americans--Work.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Battle Creek Area Urban League Guild.; Community service--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Southwestern Michigan Urban League.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Southwestern Michigan Urban League.; African Americans--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Battle Creek Area Urban League.; African Americans--Societies, etc.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Urban renewal--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Social service--Michigan--Battle Creek.; West End Redevelopment Association (Battle Creek, Mich.)
Contributors:
Battle Creek Area Urban League.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
- History 1962-2006
  The History series (.75 linear ft.; 1962-2006) includes a history of the origin of the organization written by Evelyn Golden, papers related to the founding, clippings, documentation from the organization's 40th anniversary in 2006, and a scrapbook of newspaper articles. The scrapbook provides a particularly valuable chronological overview of Southwestern Michigan Urban League from 1962 to 1989 -- articles generated both from press releases and investigative reporting.
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1967-1971, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - 40th Anniversary 2006 (Box 1)
  - Golden, Evelyn/History 1980s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous History, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers Related to Formation 1962-1967, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings 1962-1989, 8 folders (Box 1)
- Administrative 1966-2007
  The Administration series (4.25 linear ft.; 1966-2007) documents the internal structure and finances of the League. It contains bylaws, financial statements, proposals, planning and personnel documents, including documentation of periodic CEO interviewing and hiring. The series is important for the detailed financial information provided in a complete run of annual financial reports for the years 1972 to 2007 and in proposals and grant applications. As a not-for-profit organization dependent upon grant funding for both daily operations and programmatic funding, Southwestern Michigan Urban League's proposal/grant files reveal important additional information about organizational structure, mission and goals. Researchers should also consult files in the Programs series for similar documents that relate to specific programs.
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Census Summary 1970 (Box 1)
  - CEO Search
    - James Graham 1997 (Box 1)
    - Joyce Brown 2001 (Box 1)
    - Kenneth Little 2002-2004 (Box 1)
    - General 1997-2005 (Box 1)
  - Directories 1988-1999 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records
    - 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970-2000, 31 folders (Box 2)
    - 2001-2007 & Undated Miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Financial Procedural Manual 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Guidelines for Board Members (Box 3)
  - Leadership Development 1966-1971, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Membership 1979-2000, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1988-2005 (Box 3)
  - National Urban League
    - Affiliation Report
      - 1966-1968, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - 1980, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Association of Executives 1993-2000 (Box 3)
    - Central and Western Regional Assembly 2003 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1966-1972, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - The Education Initiative (Box 4)
    - Fellowships 1968 (Box 4)
    - Guidelines for Assessment (Box 4)
    - Leadership Meeting 1994 (Box 4)
    - Orientation (Box 4)
    - Performance Evaluation 1976 (Box 4)
    - Quarterly Report 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Summary of Affiliates 1990 (Box 4)
  - Orientation 1970 (Box 4)
  - Personnel
    - Correspondence 1986-1988 (Box 4)
    - Personnel Manuals, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Orientation Manual/Employment Department (Box 4)
    - Policies 1986-2004, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Position Descriptions/Evaluations, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Secretarial Training (Box 4)
    - Staff Incentive Program (Box 4)
    - Staff Rosters/Organizational Charts (Box 4)
    - Staff Training 1970-1971, 1980-1985 (Box 4)
    - Staff Training Institute 1973 (Box 4)
  - Planning
    - Action Plan 2002-2006 (Box 4)
    - Business Plan 2001-2006 (Box 4)
    - Focus Group 1996, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Planning Conference 1979 (Box 4)
    - Strategic Planning
      - 1985-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Plans and Outcomes 1997-2004 (Box 4)
      - Taskforce/Process 1995-2000 (Box 4)
      - Meetings 1997-2004 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1995-2001 (Box 4)
    - Urban League Vision 2001-2004 (Box 4)
  - Proposals/Grants/Contracts (Box 5)
    - 21st Century Leaders (Box 5)
    - Adult Basic Education 1990 (Box 5)
    - Aids Community Action 1989 (Box 5)
    - Apprenticeship Program, [1970s (Box 5)
    - Black Spirit 1984 (Box 5)
    - Brown Center for Health Education 1989 (Box 5)
    - Building Plan 1980 (Box 5)
    - Business Awards 2000-2002 (Box 5)
    - Business Development Organization 1972 (Box 5)
    - Camp Ben Johnson 1989 (Box 5)
    - Career Exploration 1990 (Box 5)
    - Child Care and Parenting Learning Center 1986 (Box 5)
    - City of Battle Creek Contracts 1997-2002 (Box 5)
    - Community Crime Prevention 1986 (Box 5)
    - Community Tutorial Task Force 1974 (Box 5)
    - Counseling Home Ownership Initiative Program 1990 (Box 5)
    - Displaced Homemakers 1979 (Box 5)
    - Educational Opportunity Center 1990 (Box 5)
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Training 1984 (Box 5)
    - Equal Results Educational Initiative, 1970s (Box 5)
    - Emergency Aid 1974 (Box 5)
    - Entrepreneurship Class 2000 (Box 5)
    - Extension of Services to Albion, MI 1972 (Box 5)
    - Leadership Development Seminar 1972-1987 (Box 5)
    - Family Learning Resource Center 1990 (Box 5)
    - Future Force circa 1970-2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Grant Street Project 1972 (Box 5)
    - Homeownership Counseling Network 1990 (Box 5)
    - Housing Seminar 1972 (Box 5)
    - Hypertension Screening 1980 (Box 5)
    - Institute to Promote Science, Math, Health 1989 (Box 5)
    - International Business Machines, 1970s (Box 5)
    - Job Connection Center 1990 (Box 5)
    - Kellogg
      - Grants 1991-2006, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Yes We Can 2002-2006 (Box 5)
      - Youth Initiative Partnership 2000 (Box 5)
    - Latin American Affairs, 1980s (Box 5)
    - Leila Arboretum 1994 (Box 5)
    - Management Training 1990 (Box 5)
    - Manpower Service Center 1974 (Box 5)
    - Minority Youth Employment 1989 (Box 5)
    - Misc Contracts/Legal Documents 1997-2005 (Box 5)
    - Mobile Unit, 1980s (Box 5)
    - Neighborhood Revitalization 1991 (Box 5)
    - On the Job Training and Educational Enrichment 1974 (Box 5)
    - Pre-employment Skills Training 1991 (Box 5)
    - Preparing for Tomorrow's World 1990 (Box 5)
    - Professional Leadership Development Institute 2003 (Box 5)
    - Resource Center 1989 (Box 5)
    - Save Area Adolescents Through Vocational Education 1990 (Box 5)
    - Second Monday Seminars 2000 (Box 5)
    - Semco 1999 (Box 5)
    - Shadow Project 1986 (Box 5)
    - Skills Bank 1974 (Box 5)
    - Substance Abuse 1990 (Box 5)
    - Summer Youth 1977 (Box 5)
    - Summer Youth Ralston 1981 (Box 5)
    - Work Experience Program 1974 (Box 5)
    - Youth Conservation Corp. 1981 (Box 5)
    - Summer Youth Career Development and Employment 1984 (Box 5)
    - Summer Youth Employment Training 1991 (Box 5)
    - Youth Conservation Corp. 1981 (Box 5)
    - Youth Conservation and Community Improvement 1980 (Box 5)
    - Youth Development Project 1979 (Box 5)
    - Youth on the Job Training 1978 (Box 5)
  - Volunteers, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Correspondence 1962-2007
  The Correspondence series (2.50 linear ft.; 1962-2007) is comprised of papers initiated by the board of directors, executive directors and program managers regarding internal management, programmatic matters and community involvement. These records most significantly reflect the tenures of Benjamin Richmond and Joyce Brown during a time of League revitalization following a period of short-term directors. Richmond's files are an important source for documenting the emergence of the Southwestern Urban League as an organization highly visible in community affairs. Brown, also active in outreach, revised internal systems and procedures, instituted regular staff meetings and relied heavily on written communication with staff. Researchers will find her files, along with staff meeting minutes in the Meetings series and departmental reports in the Reports series, useful in understanding day to day operations, planning and problem solving. Also of interest, although limited, is correspondence generated by Alonzo Matthews, executive director during a period of rapid expansion from 1973 to 1977, and that of Evelyn Golden, the first President of the Board of Directors.
  - Board of Directors
    - 1979-1988 (Box 6)
    - 2000-2007 (Box 6)
  - Board of Director Resignations
    - 1967-1971 (Box 6)
  - Brown, Joyce (President/CEO)
    - Incoming 1988-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Memos 1987-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Outgoing 1987-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - General 2002 (Box 6)
  - Cartwright, Karen (Chairperson, Board of Directors)
    - 2002-2004 (Box 6)
  - Fowler, James (Employment Program Director)
    - Incoming 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - Outgoing 1976-1981, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Franklin, Karen (Chairperson, Board of Directors)
    - 2004 (Box 6)
  - General
    - 1966-1971, 14 folders (Box 6)
    - 1972-2006 & Undated, 9 folders (Box 7)
  - Golden, Evelyn (President, Board of Directors)
    - 1962-1976 (Box 7)
  - Graham, James (President/CEO)
    - 1993-1997 (Box 7)
  - Harper, John (Chairman, Board of Directors)
    - Incoming 2001-2007 (Box 7)
    - Outgoing 2001-2005 (Box 7)
  - Howell, Keith (Acting Executive Director)
    - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Kellogg Foundation
    - 1985-1991, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Lane, Thad (Employment Program Director)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - Little, Kenneth (President/CEO)
    - 2003-2004 (Box 7)
  - Matthews, Alonzo (Executive Director)
    - 1976 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Morris, Mary (Community Services Director)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 7)
  - National Urban League
    - 1982-1987 (Box 7)
  - Ongwela, Thomas (Director of Operations)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - Richmond, Benjamin (President and CEO)
    - Incoming 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Outgoing 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Robinson, Darryl K. (Youth Services Director)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 7)
  - Roper, Herschel J. (Executive Director)
    - 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Smith, Alvin (Executive Director)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - Townes, Gwinette (Focus on Readiness in Education Program Director and Education Director)
    - Incoming 1988-1990 (Box 8)
    - Outgoing 1988-1990, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - United Way 1979-1989 (Box 8)
  - Warren, Dizzy (Acting President/CEO)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 8)
  - Wilson, Robert (Deputy Executive Director)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 8)
  - Word, Carl (President/CEO)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 8)
- Meetings 1965-2006
  The Meetings series (2.00 linear ft.; 1965-2006) includes minutes from board of director meetings (incorporating executive director monthly reports to the board), staff meetings and committees. Included in the board minutes files are name and address rosters for most years. The Meetings series also contains minutes from the Michigan Council of Urban Leagues Executives from 1974 to 1982, 1984 to 1991 and 1997.
  - Administrative Oversight Committee 1999 (Box 8)
  - Board of Directors
    - 1965-1986, 21 folders (Box 8)
    - 1987-2006, 14 folders (Box 9)
    - Assorted Dates/ Undated (Box 9)
    - Miscellany 1997-2005 (Box 9)
    - Orientation 2006 (Box 9)
    - Rosters 1967-1990 (Box 9)
  - Collaboration Committee 2003-2004 (Box 9)
  - Education and Youth Incentives Committee 1967-1970, 12 folders (Box 9)
  - Executive Committee 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Health and Welfare Committee 1973 (Box 9)
  - Housing Committee 1968-1972, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Michigan Council of Urban League Directors 1966-1971, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Michigan Council of Urban League Executives 1974-1982, 1984-1991, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Michigan Urban League CEOs 1997 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Meetings 1984-2007, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - National Urban League Conference 1970-1971 (Box 9)
  - National Urban League Council of Executive Directors 1966-1971, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Nominating Committee 1969, 1984-1989 (Box 10)
  - Personnel Committee 1971, 1979-1988, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Scholarship Committee
    - General, 197? 1986, 1988-1990, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Staff Meetings 1969-1971, 1979-1981, 1986-1991, 11 folders (Box 10)
  - Staff Planning Committee 1979 (Box 10)